[music]
>> Hey everyone.
I'm Vic and I lead applied research at
LangChain and I'm going to talk about
something that I think is sexy, which is
data mining, but it's not as sexy as
LLM, so we're going to try to like make
it sexy together. And the problem that
we're going to talk about today is how
do we continuously improve agents, but
how do we do that via data?
So, to start, I'm going to tell a little
story that I think maybe a lot of us
have felt before. Like, I ran my agent,
it did a bunch of things,
it made some mistakes.
Now, I ask someone like, what do I
actually do about that? Like, I have all
this data, made some mistakes, what now?
Basically, what we're going to do today
is we're going to motivate a recipe for
what we should do to continuously
improve agents over time, and then I'm
going to talk from some lived experience
and like some stuff that we help
customers do to run this over
large-scale trace data.
So, the first step in building a
successful agent is shipping it. So, if
you put it out into the real world, then
it can operate in environments and then
you can get feedback from what it's
doing.
The second step is collect a ton of
traces. So, agents operate in the
environment every single time they
operate, they do tool calls, they have
output messages, they call APIs, they
use CLIs. All of that generates data and
we want to store all of that so we can
like do stuff with it.
The next thing is the data mining in
this talk, which is once we have tons of
trace data, maybe gigabytes, maybe
terabytes, depending on like how many
agents you're shipping, we're going to
do data mining over that. And I promise
I will tell you exactly what data mining
we're going do, uh but we're going to do
some over it.
And then the fun part, which is I
collected that data, I read it, I
curated it, and now we actually need to
run the experiments in a data-driven way
to see, "Hey, is this new prompt, or is
this new tool, or is this new
orchestration, or is this new loop, is
it actually improving things based on
the previous traces that I've seen?"
And this is maybe a bit of a hot take,
but continual learning is super hot
right now. I'm talking about it, this
whole room is going to hear about it for
the next like 5-6 hours. Um but there's
a very tight coupling between what
observability is and what continual
learning is. And the main reason for
that is that
agents that operate in environments,
they produce trace data, and what
continual learning for agents and
continual learning for humans basically
is is I do a bunch of stuff in the
world, I think about what I did, and
then I need to update my definition,
like my knowledge, stuff I write down,
in order to respond to the feedback from
the environment. And if you're continual
learning company, you need traces, and
if you have traces, then you can try to
do continual learning over your agents.
I had to put in a meme because
if you look at your data, then you can
be like Will Hunting if anyone's seen
the movie, where like everything is
super super easy, and you can like
improve over time, and I promised Emma I
would put this in there, so putting it
in there.
Cool. So, why am I talking a bunch about
traces anyway? So,
I'm sure a ton of us were software
engineers before, we're software
engineers now, and on the left we have a
code block, and we can sort of like read
the code, and in my head, I can almost
reason over what this code does. I can
see the functions, I can see like how
they call each other.
I can roughly understand the logic in
Python. Um that doesn't exactly exist in
agent world because agents have prompts,
they have tools, they have skills, they
have hooks, they have middlewares, some
agents call other agents and I
orchestrate them in swarms. It's really
really hard for humans to reason about
how certain prompts that they change are
actually going to affect agent behavior
at scale. And this also varies between
the different domains that you're doing
it on. So, a prompt change and you're
using for the medical domain is going to
be like completely different than a
prompt change that you want to do for
the law domain.
And in general, over the last four years
since the ChatGPT moment, we've started
trading determinism for autonomy. And in
that shift, sort of what we need to do
is create tools and create systems to
still understand agents when they're
autonomously operating in environments.
So, I talked about traces. Um
why like why should you read them? And
at LangChain, what do we actually do
when we're reading traces? So, we
centralize a bunch of our data, so we
put everything in a tracing project and
this is usually either like per agent or
like centralized across all of our
agents. And then what we do is we send
agents to read traces from other agents,
right? And then we look for a bunch of
different things. And we might ask for,
"Hey, like find a bunch of like good and
bad interactions where like users got
upset or like users are like really
happy."
Um
another question I might ask is uh this
is a technical question like "Agents now
run for millions of tokens. Does the
agent get really dumb after the first
compaction? After the second compaction?
Does it never get dumb?" Like how do we
actually answer these questions? We need
to do it by actually looking at the
traces.
And then the the other thing is like if
I look at the traces, then I can try to
prove some counterfactuals, which is
"Hey, like I ran GPT 5.5 for this and I
heard like GLM is really good. What
happens if I run GLM 5.2 for this task
and how do I compare them? Metrics,
awesome. The The trace level captures
the actual like behavior that users see.
So, that's also like very helpful for
seeing behavior like fine grain scales.
And the way that we sort of think about
the data that's being generated by
agents is that the data that we see
today is going to be the smallest that
humans have ever seen in their entire
lives because we're in this massive
exponential shift to our agents are
doing more and more work in the economy.
And what that means is like the amount
of data that humans have produced in our
entire lifetime will soon be eclipsed by
agents running on like year scales and
then 6-month scales and 3-month scales
and then maybe every day, right? Um and
to understand a ton of that data,
roughly what we need to do is contend
with a couple problems. There's more,
but these are the two that I'm going to
focus on. So,
one, uh reading traces at scale is super
expensive, uh especially if you have
millions of traces and if you have
millions of tokens per trace, right? Um
think of it as like an input token cost.
You can like literally multiply the
input token cost uh times the number of
traces times like how big each trace is
on average, right? Um the the other
thing is [clears throat] if I have a
super long interaction with a coding
agent like Cloud Code or Codex or like
deep agents, um
I can't even read that trace with
another agent because that that context
like doesn't fit in memory, right? So,
it's like we we need to develop systems
so I can sort of treat that context as
like an external object and then I can
sort of query into it, right? So, we we
need to build agents to efficiently mine
data from other agents and it's it's no
longer as simple as just like feeding
the data into context and there's like
tricks that we'll sort of talk about uh
to to do that well.
Great. So, one of the things that I
think is really really cool in the last
6 months is that open models have
basically hit an inflection point in
intelligence that we at LangChain don't
reach for the frontier models for every
single use case. We're quite conscious
about what is the minimum level of
intelligence that I need to do any given
task. And like practically speaking,
honestly, yes, we start with Opus, we
start with 55 because we just want to
know if the task is even possible. But
then once we reach that sort of like
waterline, then we like look back at
those traces and we see, "Hey, can we
use an open model to do the same thing?"
So, this is a bunch of work that we did
with Harvey and then their lab legal
benchmark. Basically, what we're looking
at is
can I match the trace judging capability
of Opus with an open cheaper model? And
the answer is roughly yes at like an
order or like two orders of magnitude
cheaper. And like the way we do that is
we try a bunch of models,
we do a bunch of like harness
engineering, and the harness engineering
is informed by a bunch of the traces
that we read. So, it's like, "Hey, like
Opus reasons about things in this way.
Maybe that's because of the prompt.
Maybe Opus is just smarter, which it is,
than a bunch of the open models, but
that might mean I need to give it a
little bit more guidance so it can reach
the sort of same intelligence level at
like a much
much lower cost."
And the the other thing that we sort of
look at is like harness engineering is
amazing.
You get instant feedback and you can
sort of like run on your evals, but
eventually what we find is you hit a
threshold of intelligence where it's
like "If I keep tweaking this prompt,
I'm not going to get too much more out
of it." And once we reach that point, we
sort of look at, "Okay, can I actually
like fine-tune the model on my
domain-specific task?" And can I like
make it better on those tasks? And what
we find is if we take like base models
and we tune them on like very specific
vertical tasks, which is what a lot of
our customers do, they don't really care
about the entire variance of tasks. like
they care about what their customers
care about. So, if we focus on that
narrow set of tasks, then we can
fine-tune base models to sort of like
reach and then also go beyond frontier
performance. And I think one sort of
like small thing I'll mention as a lot
of people are getting into fine-tuning
is that another sort of like economic
decision is that you can move from token
costs to hardware costs. And this is
like can be a really big change, right?
Cuz like you're very used to hey, like a
million tokens cost this much, not as
much like this cluster sort of costs
this much. But for like very high
inference workloads, we find it to be
way cheaper just to like run a cluster
and I get like unlimited inference on
that cluster. I don't have to worry
about tokens, but I can just do the
calculation of like, hey,
um this will end up being cheaper and
then I can spin it down when I don't
need it.
Cool. And I said all of this um
so we obviously like built a product to
do that. Uh I won't shill it too much,
but it's LangSplat engine. Uh basically,
this product is trying to automate this
loop for you, which is if you have any
volume of trace data and you're looking
for something that trace data or you
want to generate e-vals from that trace
data or you want to like generate
feedback for like humans to read from
that trace data, it will go read all of
it, it'll like find issues, it'll
agentically search over it, and they can
like prepare data sets for you to do
something after. And a bit of a leader,
um
what that something basically is is the
outputs of this trace mining exercise.
So,
there's like three things that I
mentioned here uh which we see a bunch
and we kind of put into the product. So,
one is distillation and fine-tuning,
which is let's say I'm running GLM 5.2.
It's doing great, but I think that I can
run this task like way cheaper with like
a 9B or 13B model. Then what I'll do is
like I'll take the good traces and the
good examples from the GLM 5.2 runs,
I'll prepare them in a data set, and
then I'll try to fine-tune a small model
on that data set to like mimic behavior,
essentially, right? And this is like
distillation, SFT. The The other one is
generating evals and environments. So,
maybe another slightly hot take, I think
you can basically define agent behavior
by showing the evals that you ran on it,
right? Like, if someone showed me all
the things that they're trying to test
their agent on, I think I would have a
rough idea about how that agent is going
to behave because it literally like hill
climbs those evals, and you you alter
the behavior of the agent to make the
evals pass, right? Like, the purpose of
evals is roughly to try to make them
pass, right? So, I update my agent so
that they essentially pass. And then the
the other thing is um like humans are
still in the loop. Like, I need to know
that customers are happy. I also want to
know what my agents are doing. I just
don't have the bandwidth to read a bunch
of traces. So, preparing content for
humans is still like really, really
valuable today, especially in like
high-trust domains like legal and
medical. Like, some human needs to
review this, um but they can't read it
all, so we try to make it easy for them
to process all that data.
Great. This is um maybe a bit of a
throwback. Like, how many people here
know what like scikit-learn is? Uh maybe
put your uh psych This crowd is just
awesome. Um cool. So, uh when I was like
first doing my PhD, uh
my PhD was like kind of trying to do
this, but like add new algorithms to
scikit-learn. And like, what
scikit-learn basically is uh an abstract
level, it's a bunch of helpers to fit
learning systems to data, right? And
like, classical machine learning, I had
like a data set, I tried to fit it to
it, but I think the same principles that
we use in modern in I got I call it
classical machine learning, it's like 6
years ago. Um that we do in classical
machine learning uh definitely still
apply to this agent-first world. Um,
the way that they apply is what I like
to call model harness task fit. So, we
still have this sort of like fit
function that I'm going to try to like
take my data, take a harness, take a
model, and I'm going to try to fit it
all together to make sure that all of my
tasks pass, right? The algorithms look
slightly different, uh but the overall
process of machine learning doesn't
really look that different, and we'll
talk about maybe roughly what our job
becomes in this data-first, agent-first,
fit-first world. So, a couple of our
main jobs now are
find good fit functions. So, these are
like auto research. This is tons of
great work that's being done in RL on
different methods like OPD, OPSD,
trySFT.
And also find good data, right? So, if
you put those two things together, then
that is basically the applied or just
overall research question that every
team has to make their agents better.
I like some some examples that we've
seen that are like very popular that
we're pretty bullish on are just
generally auto research. So, if you have
some sort of score that you can make
number go up, uh
agents are pretty good at making that
number go up. They might cheat a little
bit and you need to like check them on
some stuff. Um, but this sort of like
general feedback loop of do something,
read the results, read the traces, and
then do an update ends up being pretty
useful. And then I talked about like
model fine-tuning a bunch as well.
Um,
so we we just like went and did this. Uh
this was I think even before the term
auto research came out, but a lot of
people were doing it, which is hey, like
terminal benches like really hard. Uh
what would happen if an agent just like
read its traces, uh proposed
experiments, and then tried to do fixes?
Um, I think one like really key thing
here is uh
giving agents dense feedback signals.
So, like terminal bench, the output is
just a number, right? Like, did you pass
or did you not pass? Uh that's like kind
of helpful, but if I give you like a
super random task, like you just did a
bunch of stuff, and then I just said
like you failed or you passed, uh if you
failed, like you wouldn't really have a
good signal to figure out what you
should do next, right? So, densifying
feedback is uh really good way to
improve agents, and like traces are the
substrate that hold that feedback. And
then agents are very good at like
reading those uh those traces and then
figuring out like what to do next. Um
and then this sort of question always
comes up, which is
when should I like harness Enge? When
should I fine-tune? Uh should I do more
harness Enge after it? I'm like pretty
bullish on the idea of if you need to do
something for improving your agent, the
best thing that you can do is collect
feedback as quickly as possible, like
either from humans labeling or just
letting the agents run. So, like harness
engineering gives you feedback in maybe
2 minutes. Um
once you sort of saturate the harness
engineering ceiling, right? Then you can
maybe try to do like fine-tuning after
that, but we find a lot of teams are
happy with harness engineering and uh it
solves their customer use case, so like
we always sort of sort of recommend it.
And then we have this like sort of
sandwich, which is like try harness
engineering, try to do fine-tuning to
sort of like break through that ceiling,
and then do more harness engineering
again if you need to.
And then I'll sort of end on the the
idea generally of continual learning is
that there's an agent taking actions in
the environment, and then it needs to
use that information, sorry guys, needs
to use that information to update
information about itself, right? So,
it's like I did a bunch of these tasks,
and like I need to update my prompts to
make sure I do them more efficiently. Or
users are users keep asking to search
for these types of things, I should
maybe tell like tell my creator that
like they're they're doing this sort of
stuff, right? It's like taking action in
the environment kind of like humans do
and updating ourselves. What that looks
like today, slightly unclear, but we
think that you're going to have to do it
across all three axes, which is one,
collect a bunch of training data, which
is like observational data from agents
taking actions. The The other one is
like harness updates generally, like
you know, the the Codex harness and the
Cloud Code harness and like our harness
and everyone's harness, like they look a
certain way because like models are are
trained in them and they look a certain
way because of the tasks that they do in
the real world and we think like
evolving those over time is going to be
super important in in order to make them
work. And
the the last thing is like memory. So,
uh
we humans are like really good at like
remembering stuff over time, but we are
not append-only logs of information. And
if agents are going to be working with
us over like year, 5-year, decade,
lifetime time scales, we cannot just
append everything to like a really big
file and then search over it. There's a
ton of stuff that needs to happen with
like updating those files over time and
then just making memory like really
efficient. But, we think a lot of that
actually comes from this idea of scaling
sleep time compute and and dreaming
generally. So, it's like read all of the
traces over the entire agent life cycle
and then like do [music] things to
update agent state.
Awesome. So, like quick quick takeaways,
uh mining traces gives you signals to
hill climb on. Uh I would say like if
you have an agent, just turn on tracing
and point an agent at it and that's like
the easiest thing that you can do to see
like to basically understand what your
agents are doing.
Uh we're very excited about open models.
We want to help you fine-tune open
models. Um we provide them as a service
as well. So, if you're interested in
that, would would love to chat how you
can use open models to make everything
smarter and cheaper. Um,
continual learning is about operating
environments and then integrating that
data back into agent state. And then
finally, I think this is so cool that
like we have systems that's going to
pre- that are going to produce more data
than we ever have before.
Uh, we need to all come up with like
interesting research directions to learn
how to like manage that at scale and
like make all of our agents better.
And with that,
thank you. Thank you all for coming.
>> [applause]
[music]